A Guide to the John R. Camp Papers FA069
Rockefeller Archive Center
John R. Camp papers
1903-1981, bulk 1943-1981
1943-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Camp, John R.
FA069
2.6 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted are noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement note
The collection is divided into three series:
Series 1 - South America Series 2 - Michigan Hill Series 1042 - Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
John Camp was born November 19, 1909, in Ashland County, Ohio. He was one of four children of John W. and Ellen McNab Camp.
He attended public schools in Wayne County and graduated from Wooster High School in 1928. He graduated from Colorado College in Colorado Springs, Colorado, in 1932 with a Bachelor of Science degree in forestry.
After graduating from Cornell University in Ithaca, New York with a Master of Science degree in 1933, John Camp was employed as a forestry technician with the United States Forest Service and became director of the Planning Division in Washington, D. C.
In 1942 he was loaned by the Forest Service to the War Relocation Authority and became assistant director of the industrial division.
In 1943 he was employed by the Institute of Inter-American Affairs in Paraguay as head of the Institute's agricultural mission. In May of 1945 he was transferred to Venezuela as head of the Institute's agricultural mission and director of the Service Cooperativo Inter Americano de Produccion de Alimentos.
In 1947 he joined the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) as a representative in Venezuela.
In 1948 he became director of the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). In cooperation with the Venezuelan government, he organized the Consejo Inter Americano de Educacion Alimenticia (CIDEA) and the Consejo de Bienestar Rural (CBR) and served on the boards of directors of the agencies. In 1960 he was named by the AIA board as Executive Vice President in charge of all activities of that organization in Latin America.
In 1969 he retired from the AIA and from 1970 to 1977 was employed as a consultant for Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller's 'Michigan Hill' project.
He was a member of the Society of American Foresters, the International Society of Tropical Foresters, the Society of International Development, the Cosmos Club of Washington, D. C., the Cornell Club of New York, and Delta Epsilon, a national honorary scientific society.
He married Emily Patch of Berkshire, New York, in 1934. They had two children. John Camp died in 2005.
Scope and Contents note
The material in this collection covers John Camp's service as director of the agricultural program in Paraguay and Venezuela in the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (1943-1946); representative of the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) in Venezuela (1947-1960); representative in Venezuela (1947-1963), vice-president (1955-1960), and executive vice-president (1961-1969) of the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA); and as consultant (1969-1980) for Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller's 'Michigan Hill' Project, John D. Rockefeller's birthplace, in Tioga County, New York.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 3A 05
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The John R. Camp Collection was given to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1979 and 1982.
Paraguay; South America; Agriculture -- Venezuela; Venezuela; Agriculture -- Paraguay; Agriculture; Michigan Hill State Forest (N.Y.); Richford (N.Y.); New York (State); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); International Basic Economy Corporation; United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs; American International Association for Economic and Social Development
- South America, 1943-1969; 1; 0.8 Cubic Feet 3 document cases
  Arrangement note
  This series is divided into three subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Personal Correspondence, Subseries 2 - Reports, Subseries 3 - Oversized Material
  - South America - Personal Correspondence, 1943-1969; 1.1
    - 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - South America - Reports, 1947-1963; 1.2
    Scope and Contents note
    There are five reports in this subseries, several of which are written in Spanish.
    - "History of the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs", 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Agricultural Development in Venezuela (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Conservation in Venezuela, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 'Americas', August, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Trip to Liberia, Ghana, and Nigeria, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - South America - Oversized Material, 1.3
    Subseries 3 consists of an autograph album (1945), a report of the Chief of Party in the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (1943), and an annual report from the same office (1944).
    - 'El Personal Del Stica A John R. Camp' - Asuncion, Paraguay, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 11A)
    - 'Program in Paraguay', 1943 (Box 3, Folder 11B)
      Report to the Chief of Party.
    - 'Informe Anual', 1944 (Box 3, Folder 11C)
      Instituto do Asuntos Inter Americanos
- Michigan Hill, 1903-1981; 2; 1 Cubic Feet 3 document cases
  This series is divided into four subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Personal Files, Subseries 2 - Agent Files, Subseries 3 - Reports, Subseries 4 - Artifacts and Maps
  Separated Materials
  Large maps have been removed to the map collection.
  - Michigan Hill - Personal Files, 2.1
    Included in this subseries is correspondence dating from 1967-1980.
    - Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1980, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Michigan Hill - Agent Files, 2.2
    This subseries concerns the acquisition of property in the John D. Rockefeller Homestead area and includes deeds and clippings pertaining to the Rockefeller family and the Tioga Park (1903-1981).
    - 1970-August 7, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted material.
    - Receipts (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Property Acquisition - Schmale, Otto, April 15, 1968-June 29, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Property Acquisition - John D. Rockefeller Homestead, March 28, 1968-July 22, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Property Acquisition - Eggleston, Merritt J. and Kathleen J., December 8, 1970-July 22, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Property Acquisition - Zupancic, John and Bernice, September 27, 1944-May 7, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Property Acquisition - Gutchess Lumber Company, July 1, 1966-October 20, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Property Acquisition - Pardi, Dolores, and La Salle, Dolores, March 15, 1971-October 1, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Property Acquisition - Hubbard, Edgar and Dorothy A., May 22, 1972-January 27, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Property Acquisition - Patton, Mary C.; Tuthill, William; Thorp, Jack and Gabrielle, September 15, 1971-December 7, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Property Acquisition - Kachdourian, Mr. and Mrs. P., September 14, 1937-January 3, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Property Acquisition - Short, Clayton, August 10, 1938-April 10, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Property Acquisition - Zahl, Samuel and Viola, September 5, 1969-April 11, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Deeds - Lot 550, 549 - Homestead, key (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Deeds - Lot 550 - Clute (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Deeds - Lot 550 - Rockefeller (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Deeds - Lot 550 - School (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Deeds - Lot 550 - Sawmill Site (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Deeds - Lot 571 - Zimmer (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Deeds - Lot 570 - Tucker (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Deeds - Lot 551 - Walker (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Deeds - Lot 569 - Whelpley/Bemis (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Deeds - Lot 550, 570, 571 - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Deeds - Richford Mortgages (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Clippings - John D. Rockefeller Birthplace, 1929-1980 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Clippings - Lumber, 1929-1979 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Clippings - Rockefeller Family, 1903-1975 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Clippings - Ray Rockefeller - 'Rock's Rambles', 1964-1976 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Clippings - Tioga Park, 1971-1981 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Clippings - Miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Michigan Hill - Reports, 2.3
    There are eight reports in this subseries; six of these reports have photographic supplements. Of note is Folder 48, which contains a report describing the entire Michigan Hill project and Camp's role in it.
    - Photo Display, May 11, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - "The Michigan Hill Project" - John R. Camp, November 30, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - "The Birthplace of John D. Rockefeller" - Joseph W. Ernst, September 26, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - "Restorations on Michigan Hill" - Joseph W. Ernst, May 1, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - "Planning for the Michigan Hill Area" - John R. Camp, May 11, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - "Notes and Drawings About Early Sawmills of Central New York" - William Houghton, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Photographic Report - John R. Camp, April 1971 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - "John D. Rockefeller Homestead - 1920's" - Mrs. Kenneth Mead, April 1974 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Photographs of Archaeological Work, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Maps (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Michigan Hill - Artifacts and Maps, 2.4
    Due to the nature and potentially brittle condition of this material, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
    - Keys to John Zupancic House, Michigan Hill, memorabilia (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Keys to Lock on School House, Michigan Hill, Richmond (Tioga County), memorabilia (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Nail, memorabilia (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Two Pottery Sherds, memorabilia (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Michigan Hill - Aerial Photograph (Box A, Folder 9)
    - Michigan Hill (Box B, Folder 10)
    - State of New York, Office of Planning Coordination, Tioga County - Southern Tier East Region Map (Box C, Folder 11)
    - Michigan Hill site plans, circa 1972-1974; MAPS AND ARCHITECTURAL DRAWINGS (Quantity 39). Oversized. (Drawer B 10, Folder 1)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Retrieval times for maps and flat files may exceed 24 hours. Individual items may be restricted from scholarly access at the discretion of RAC.
    - Michigan Hill property maps, circa 1935-1976; MAPS (Quantity 12) (Drawer B 10, Folder 2)
    - Michigan Hill Regional Maps (Box F 126, Folder 3)
    - Michigan Hill (Box F 127, Folder 4)
    - Michigan Hill Archaeological Maps (Box F 128, Folder 5)
    - Michigan Hill Property Parcels (Box F 129, Folder 6)
    - Michigan Hill (Box F 130, Folder 7)
    - Michigan Hill (Box F 131, Folder 8)
- John R. Camp photographs, 1042
  Camp, John R.
  - John R. Camp (Box 20, Folder 256)
  - John R. Camp (Box 20, Folder 257)
  - John R. Camp: Negatives (Box 21, Folder 258)
  - John R. Camp (Box 21, Folder 259)
  - John R. Camp (Box 21, Folder 260)
  - John R. Camp (Box 21, Folder 261)
  - John R. Camp (Box 21, Folder 262)